Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Corning Museum of Glass, Corning, New York 1972-1988, 474 drawings; 4 linear feet
  - Architectural Drawings
    - Corning Glass Center Renovation Drawings
      - Construction Documents
        - Electrical Drawings. Sepia prints, 4/3/78, revised 05/10/1978
          - Upper Level Plan (E1) (Map-case 26, Folder 23)
    - Corning Museum of Glass Presentation Boards
      - [Lower Level Floor Plan], untitled. Silver, green, purple, gray and blue paper cut-outs on two illustration boards undated (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - [Upper Level Floor Plan], untitled. Silver, green, gray and purple paper cut-outs on two illustration boards undated (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - [Upper Level Floor Plan], untitled. Blue and purple paper cut-outs on one illustration board undated (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - [Entry Floor and Reflected Ceiling Plans], untitled. Silver, green, purple and blue paper cut-outs on one illustration board undated (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - [Elevation and Section], untitled. Black, purple, green and gray paper cut-outs on one illustration board undated (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - Colored Photographic Print of Museum Facade. Poster on 20x36-inch foam board, undated. Oversized, located separately (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
      - Colored Photograph of Museum Facade on Cover of GA Architect 2: Gunnar Birkerts and Associates by William Marlin. Tokyo:A.D.A. EDITA Tokyo Co., Ltd., 1982. Mounted on foam board. Oversized, located separately (Map-case 26, Folder 24)
- Ferguson Residence-"Villa Ginny", Kalamazoo, Michigan 1980-1989, 155 drawings; 0.5 linear feet
  Structural Engineer: Robert M. Darvas and Associates, P.C.
  Mechanical/Electrical Engineer: Potapa Mancini and Associates
  Contractor: Neil Blok
  Agreement Date: November 18, 1980
  Earliest Dated Drawing: September19, 1980
  Latest Dated Construction Drawing: June 26, 1984
  In his "Architect's Conceptual Statement" regarding his Ferguson Residence ("Villa Ginny") (0.5 linear feet, 155 drawings; 1980-1989), in Kalamazoo, Michigan, Mr. Birkerts states that the building is an "organic expression" of the dramatic, natural beauty of the two ravines which traverse the wooded site. He describes the organic design of this house in 1980 as a significant turning point in his career, "a newly found freedom facet for me within the many faceted movement of Modern Architecture." Appearing as if it has naturally grown from the ravine, the building juxtaposes a fluid exterior wall, which mimics the contours of the landscape, with the orthogonal organization of its inner core, which houses the functional services of the residence but does not touch the perimeter walls. There is a further balance between the organic, exterior cladding of teak, copper and stucco and the high-technology interior, with its angular, white, plastered walls. This house offers a private, serene retreat with natural views on six sides to clients Robert and Virginia Ferguson, with whose programmatic needs and values Mr. Birkerts strongly related.
  The Ferguson Residence series contains .5 linear foot of textual records, which document the design and construction of the building, and 155 architectural and engineering drawings, which graphically record the evolution of the creative design process from the "Schematic Design" through the "Design Development" and "Construction Document" sequences. The pairing of the narrative and visual records offers architectural historians, design students, preservationists and other scholars a broad and deep perspective on the development of the building, from its initial conception to its completion and its securing of a place in history.
  Researchers wishing to understand the ideas which inspired Mr. Birkerts' design of the building are referred to the "Architect's Conceptual Statement" and his poem entitled "Villa Ginny" within the textual records of the series. The requirements of Gunnar Birkerts and Associates regarding the construction of the house are written in the "Specifications" of 10/16/81. These and narrative "Bulletins #1-4" correspond directly to the visual "Construction Documents" of 12/22/81 contained within the visual materials. "Memoranda #1-38" and "Correspondence In and Out" document meetings, decisions, revisions and other construction business for those interested in the interaction of the firm with the clients, contractor and consulting engineers. Finally, narrative materials relating to the interior design and furnishings of the building are of value in showing the mastery of design of both the inside as well as the outside of the Ferguson Residence.
  The 155 drawings which comprise the visual records in this series are arranged chronologically by design. Although some later original "Schematic Design" drawings may be found here, the earliest conceptual sketches of the Ferguson Residence are contained separately in the Gunnar Birkerts Collection. Researchers interested in viewing 19 of these conceptuals, showing the metamorphosis of the initial design, are encouraged to consult the finding aid for this second collection, which amasses sketches by the architect's own hand for most of his projects.
  The "Design Development" documents of this series in the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection are mostly original pencil or ink drawings on tracing paper, vellum and mylar. However, some blue-line and sepia prints have been kept in this series if they are substitutes for originals or if they are annotated and therefore help to show the evolution of the architectural design process. The "Design Development Presentation Drawings" are of special interest. These ten ink on vellum drawings artistically depict the site and floor plans, elevations and sections of this beautiful, organic building. The "Construction Documents" include the working architectural, structural, mechanical and electrical drawings of 12/22/81, revised through 5/24/82, as well as "Supplementary Construction Details."
  - Ferguson Residence Architectural Records
    - Architect's Conceptual Statement and Poem, "Villa Ginny." (Box 66)
    - "Ferguson Residence." Architecture and Urbanism, July, 1985 (Box 66)
    - Agreement between Architect and Owner 1980 and House Location Map (Box 66)
    - Specifications October 16, 1981 (Box 66)
    - Bulletins # 1-4 1982-1984 (Box 66)
    - Memoranda # 1-38 1981-1984 (Box 66)
    - Transmittals and Correspondence Out 1980-1981 (Box 66)
    - Transmittals and Correspondence In 1980-1981 (Box 66)
    - Transmittals and Correspondence Out 1982-1984 (Box 66)
    - Transmittals and Correspondence In 1982-1984 (Box 66)
    - Correspondence Out and In, 1986-89 (Box 66)
    - Invoices for Professional Architectural Services Rendered 1981-1982 (Box 66)
    - Invoices 1981-1983 (Box 66)
    - Interior Design
      - Transmittals Out 1981-1983 (Box 66)
      - Correspondence Out 1982-1983 (Box 66)
      - Telephone Memoranda 1981-1982 (Box 66)
      - Correspondence In 1982-1983 (Box 66)
      - Memoranda 1982-1983 (Box 66)
      - Budgets 1981-1983 (Box 66)
      - Invoices 1982-1983 (Box 66)
      - Plumbing Specifications 1982 (Box 66)
      - Floor Tile Problem (Box 66)
      - Leather Problem (Box 66)
      - Furniture Catalogues (Box 66)
      - Photographs of Ferguson's Fine Art 1982 (Box 66)
    - Newspaper and Journal Articles 1983-1988 (Box 66)
    - Construction Photographs 1982, 38 slides color (Box 66)
    - Bentley Historical Library Holiday Card December, 1998 (Box 66)
  - Ferguson Residence Drawings
    - Schematic Design Drawings
      - Ink or pencil drawings on vellum, except as noted
        - [Topographical Map], untitled. 09/19/1980 (Map-case 27, Folder 1)
        - [Topographical Maps], untitled. Two drawings, one dated 09/19/1980 and one, undated (Map-case 27, Folder 1)
        - Sections Looking East and South. 11/21/1980 (Map-case 27, Folder 1)
        - Space Requirements. 11/21/1980 (Map-case 27, Folder 1)
        - Space Requirements and Relationships. Two blue-line prints, one dated 11/21/1980 and one, undated (Map-case 27, Folder 1)
      - Ink and pencil sketches on tracing paper
        - Roof Framing [Plan]. 03/19/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Floor Framing at Level Three. 03/19/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Third Level Plan. 03/20/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Level Three [Plan]. 3/20/81 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - [Floor Plan], untitled. 03/20/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Master Bath Layout. 03/21/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Fireplace. 03/25/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - Typical Stair Run. 03/25/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
        - [Site Plan] (SK-1), untitled. 03/25/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 2)
      - Interior Drawings. Pencil and ink drawings on tracing paper, undated, except as noted
        - Interior Design Plans. Fifteen drawings of lower, main and upper levels and kitchen. One dated 03/25/1981 and two dated, 03/30/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
        - Library Couch Plan, Elevations, and Sections(SK-1-8). Eight drawings, two dated 05/11/1982 five dated, 05/19/1982 and one dated, 07/14/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
        - [Bedroom Closet Elevations] (#1-4), untitled. Four drawings (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
        - [Cabinet and Closet Elevations], untitled. Twelve sketches (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
        - [Interior Wall Elevations], untitled. Two drawings (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
        - Untitled Drawing (Map-case 27, Folder 3)
    - Design Development Drawings
      - [Axonometric Floor Plans], untitled. Two pencil on vellum drawings undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Site Plans. Three blue-line prints, two dated 01/24/1981 and one, undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Second Level Plans. Two colored pencil drawings on blue-line prints undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Third Level Plans. Two blue-line prints, one dated 01/24/1981 and one, undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Sections. Blue-line print 01/24/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Site Plan, Floor Plans and Sections (#1-5). Four pencil on vellum drawings and one blue-line print, revised 03/02/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Section through Garage (A-7). Pencil on vellum drawing 04/18/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Interior Wall Elevations. Two pencil on mylar drawings 04/18/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Level One, Stair Detail (A-2). Pencil drawing on sketch paper taped to blue-line print 05/21/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Sill Detail. Two pencil on vellum drawings undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Interior Design Floor Plans. Second and Third Levels. Two blue-line prints undated (Map-case 27, Folder 4)
      - Presentation Drawings
        - [Site Plan, Floor Plans, Elevations and Sections], untitled. Ten ink on vellum drawings undated (Map-case 27, Folder 5)
    - Construction Documents
      - Architectural Drawings. Pencil on mylar drawings 12/22/1981 except as noted
        - Site Plan (A-1). Pencil on vellum drawing, revised 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Lower Level Plan (A-2). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Main Level Plan (A-3). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Upper Level Plan (A-4). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Roof Plan (A-5). Revised 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - North and South Elevations (A-6). Revised 03/10/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - East and West Elevations (A-7). Revised 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Building Sections (A-8). Revised 05/24/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Wall Sections (A-9). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Wall Sections (A-10). Revised 03/10/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Details (A-11). Revised 03/24/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 6)
        - Interior Elevations (A-12 to A-14). Three drawings, revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Fireplace Details (A-15). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Details (A-16). Revised 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Woodwork Details (A-17). 01/22/1982 revised, 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Details (A-18). 01/22/1982 revised, 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Details (A-19). 01/22/1982 revised, 04/12/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
        - Details (A-20). 03/24/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 7)
      - Structural Drawings by Robert Darvas Associates, P.C. Pencil on mylar drawings
        - Foundation Plan (S-1). 07/22/1981 revised, 11/11/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Concrete Slab Framing Plans (S-2). 07/22/1981 revised, 11/11/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Second Level Framing Plan (S-3). Revised 11/02/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Roof Framing Plan (S-4). Revised 11/02/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
      - Structural Drawings. Revisions and Clarifications. Pencil on vellum drawings
        - Level One (CL-1). 09/26/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Entry Details (CL-2). 10/06/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - [Structural Revision], untitled (SR-1). 10/19/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Major Opening Sizes and Locations at Level Two, Concrete Deck (CL-3). 10/20/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
        - Clarification (CL-4). 12/03/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 8)
      - Mechanical Drawings. Sepia prints 06/06/1981
        - Site Plan (M-1) (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Level One Plan (M-2) (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Level Two Plan (M-3) (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Level Three Plan (M-4) (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
      - Mechanical Shop Drawings by DeHaan Heating & Refrigerating Company. Three blue-line prints with colored pencil notations, received 09/16/1981
        - Basement and Soffit Heating Layout (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - First Floor Heating Layout (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Second Floor Heating Layout (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
      - Mechanical Drawings. Clarifications. Pencil and red pencil drawings on blue-line and reverse sepia prints
        - Air Distribution Clarification, Level One (MC-1). Two prints 10/15/1981 and 12/22/81. (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Air Distribution Clarification, Level Two (MC-2). Two prints 10/13/1981 and12/22/81 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Air Distribution Clarification, Level Three (MC-3). 12/22/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Air Distribution Clarification, Roof Plan (MC-4). 12/22/1981 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
      - Electrical Drawings and Revisions. Pencil and red pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints, except as noted
        - Level One (E-1). Two prints 12/22/1981, 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Level Two (ER-2 & E-2). Three prints 11/24/1981, 12/22/1981, 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Level Three (E-3). Two prints 12/22/1981, 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
        - Specifications and Schedules (E-4). One mylar chart 12/17/1981 and one chart on reverse sepia print with red pencil notations, 01/22/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 9)
      - Supplementary Construction Details
        - Clarification of Woodwork Details (CL-5). Red pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 06/08/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 10)
        - [Exterior Design Details] (CV-1 to CV-6), untitled. Six pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints, two dated 10/14/1982 and four dated, 10/20/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 10)
        - Hinge Detail (SK-20). Pencil on vellum drawing 12/02/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 10)
        - [Cabinet Drawer Details, Sections and Elevations] (SK#B-1 to B-4), untitled. Five pencil on vellum drawings 12/29/1982 (Map-case 27, Folder 10)
        - Window Detail (A-11). Pencil drawing on tracing paper 06/26/1984 (Map-case 27, Folder 10)
- St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana 1981-1988, 997 drawings; 3 linear feet
  Structural Engineer: Robert Darvas Associates, P.C.
  Mechanical/Electrical Engineer: Herbert Kunstadt Associates, P.C.
  General Contractor: Force Construction Company, Inc.
  Landscape Architect: John Grissim and Associates, Incorporated
  Earliest Dated Drawing: April 1, 1981
  Latest Dated Drawing: September 1, 1988
  St. Peter's Lutheran Church (3 linear feet, 997 drawings; 1981-1988), designed in 1981, redesigned in 1985-86 and completed in 1988, is located in Columbus, Indiana, across the street from Lincoln Elementary School (1967), which is also included in the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection. Columbus, Indiana, is nationally known for its collection of 25 school and civic buildings designed under the auspices of the Cummins Engine Foundation by such other masters of modern architecture as I. M. Pei, Robert Venturi, Kevin Roche and John Dinkeloo, Edward Larrabee Barnes and Richard Meier. St. Peter's Lutheran Church was privately commissioned by the congregation which had been impressed by Mr. Birkerts' architectural solutions in his design of Lincoln Elementary School and desired a building of similar materials and sensitivity to its Fifth Street context.
  With its modern, rounded brick and concrete form juxtaposed with a 115-foot copper-sheathed spire which pays homage to early Nordic Lutheran traditions, St. Peter's celebrates the duality of opposites which occur in nature and in life. Mr. Birkerts' hallmark fascination with organic dichotomy is expressed in the intersection of curvilinear and orthogonal geometries, the contrast of symmetry and asymmetry, and the tension of building materials in this architectural masterpiece. Seating space for 1000 members of the congregation is arranged in rising levels of concentric, but irregular circles which engender a feeling of intimacy and inclusiveness within the awe-inspiring space of the nave. Although the altar cross is located on-axis with the center aisle, its left arm projects beyond the sanctuary wall, further emphasizing the organic asymmetry of the design. Mr. Birkerts' signature use of indirect daylight in his architecture is also evident here in the placement of fin walls to allow north light into the altar space. A monumental 12-foot-wide chandelier mimics the circle-within-a-circle geometry of the nave and leads the eye upward into the conical spire.
  The St. Peter's Lutheran Church series within the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection includes three linear feet of textual records, which describe the design and construction of the building, and 997 architectural drawings, which illuminate the creative process from the "Schematic Design" through the "Design Development" and "Construction Document" sequences. This combination of the narrative and visual records offers design students, architectural historians and other scholars an unusually broad and deep perspective on the design and business activities of an internationally prominent architectural firm at the end of the twentieth century. Furthermore, these drawings represent some of the last hand-produced design and construction documents of this era, as computer-aided design begins to dominate the work of architectural firms across the nation.
  Researchers interested in understanding Mr. Birkerts thoughts and ideas relating the his design of St. Peter's Lutheran Church are directed to the "Architect's Conceptual Statement" within the textual records. Further critical illumination of his work is provided through two articles from Faith and Form and Interiors which follow. The narrative records also include the written "Specifications" for both the "Unbuilt (6/24/85) and Built (4/21/86) Schemes," which document the changes made when construction bids for the first design were deemed to be too high. At this juncture, Mr. Birkerts worked with the congregation to redesign the roof from a flatter shape with fan-shaped planes to the final conical form. Although the second scheme was not as satisfying to the architect, he views the change as a part of the natural evolution of design which occurs when all subjective and objective factors are considered. The two sets of "Specifications," representing the firm's requirements for the construction of the building, are the written counterpart to the "Construction Documents" of the same dates, which impart the identical information in visual form.
  The narrative records of the St. Peter's Lutheran Church series are arranged chronologically and include "Program Analyses" and "Cost Estimates" from the "Schematic Design" and "Design Development" phases of the architectural process, as well as "Field Reports," "Bulletins" and "Change Orders" from the construction stage. "Memoranda # 1-116" document in writing all decisions and actions taken by Gunnar Birkerts and Associates from 1981 through 1988 and thus provide a narrative history of the design and construction of this building. "Correspondence In and Out" between the firm and the client, consulting engineers and contractor also offers rich documentation of the project. Finally, 250 color 4x6" photographic prints of the construction progress are housed within the narrative records and graphically depict the building process.
  The 997 visual documents in this series are arranged chronologically according to architectural phase, from the" Schematic Design" through the "Design Development" and "Construction Document" sequences for both the "Unbuilt and Built Schemes." Researchers interested in viewing 85 original, conceptual drawings of St. Peter's Lutheran Church by Gunnar Birkerts are encouraged to consult the finding aid for the Gunnar Birkerts Collection, which houses early sketches for most of his buildings by the architect's own hand. This important, second collection contains 11 conceptual sketches of the Church and 74 sketches of the interior millwork, representing the design of the "Eternal Flame, Door, Pews" and other features constructed in maple.
  The visual documents in the St. Peter's Lutheran Church series within the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection include original pencil "Schematic Design" and "Design Development" drawings on tracing paper and vellum as well as some blue-line and sepia prints. Prints have been retained in this collection when they are substitutes for missing, original drawings or when they contain pencil annotations which show the evolution of the design process. Even drawings and prints on which the word "void" is written have been kept in chronological sequence in folders because they show the ongoing search for solutions to problems which is part of architectural design. The "Construction Documents for Unbuilt Scheme I" (6/24/85) are annotated blue-line prints and include structural, mechanical and electrical drawings of the consulting engineers.
  The chronological arrangement of the drawings in this series tells the story of the redesign of the roof after the first "Construction Documents" and "Specifications" were issued on 6/24/85, resulting in contractors' bids which were considered to be too high. Folders 27-34 contain "Design Development" drawings which represent the search for more economical solutions, culminating in "Built Scheme II." The architectural and structural "Construction Documents" for the final scheme (4/21/86) include electrostatic prints on mylar with colored pencil annotations and sepia prints, all of which are revised through 10/87. Recognizing that the interior design emphasizes the Scandinavian juxtaposition of white walls with rich maple woodwork, researchers may also be interested in the millwork construction drawings for the "Pulpit, Lectern, Baptismal Font, Curved Pews, Modesty Screen, Communion Rail, Cross, Gethsemane Window Enclosure, Eternal Flame" and other important features.
  - St. Peter's Lutheran Church Architectural Records
    - Architect's Conceptual Statement (Box 67)
    - Kaiser, Kay. "Another Jewel in the Crown." Faith & Form. Winter, 1988-1989, 9-13 (Box 67)